After we learn 1D kinematics, the next
step
will obviously be to learn two-dimension
kinematics.
The difference is self-explanatory.
You move from one dimension to two
dimensions.
But this time, we're actually going to be
using
a cool little trick to help us split the
vectors
into x and y components. Before, if the
velocity
was this way, it would be something like 5
metres
per second to the right. But now that we
have
two dimensions, it can go either up or
vertically
or horizontally. So now a vector might
look
like this. And a question might say that a
ball
is launched with a velocity of, what, 5
metres
per second with an angle of 30 degrees to
the
horizontal. And it has your magnitude and
it
has a direction. We know the direction is
degrees to the horizontal, which means
it's
going this way. And now what if the
question
asks, if the ball maintains its
speed, its velocity, how far
will it land? How far will it travel
horizontally
after 10 seconds?
Now, what does this mean by how far will
it
travel horizontally? Well, let's say this
is
the path of the ball. Since there's no
gravity
or nothing else, it maintains its
velocity.
It's just going to keep going up. Let's
just
imagine that for the sake of this
question.
Now, we know that after 10 seconds, the
distance
it's going to travel is, let's say, x
after
10 seconds. But the question wants us to
ask,
wants us to solve its distance in terms of
the
horizontal. So we're not actually trying
to
solve for x. If we were, it would just be
times 10. But we're trying to solve for,
let's
call this y. We want to solve for the
horizontal
distance, not the total distance. So how
do
we do that? Well, we need to get the
horizontal
velocity. So let me give you this.
If the ball is going this way, do you
agree
that there is going to be a motion of the
ball
that's going to the right? There will be.
It's going here, which means it's going
right.
And do you also agree that there will be
another
component of the ball that is going up?
Is the ball also going up as well as
right?
It is. It's both going up and right.
So if we have the angle, we can actually
calculate
the speed at which it's going up and the
speed
at which it's going right.
And we call that the x component and the y
component.
Let's first try to solve it. So if this is
degrees, and we know this is 5 metres per
second,
we want to calculate the distance it
travels
horizontally, which means we want to
calculate
the x component. Now, the x component is
just
5 times cosine of 30.
You can treat velocities as a triangle.
If it makes it easier to visualize, I'll
draw
this out. So there's going to be this
component,
v of x, and this would be v of y.
And v of x, you can treat it as a
triangle,
would just be equal to 5 cos 30 degrees,
since cosine is adjacent over hypotenuse.
So the adjacent would just be 5 cos 30,
which
is v of x. Now, we don't need v of y.
We only need v of x. And that means that
that
means that it's going to travel 5 cos 30
degrees
horizontally every second, horizontally
only.
So now we basically have the question
down.
The answer would be distance equals
velocity
times time. And we know velocity is 5 cos
degrees times time, which is 10.
So it would be 50 times root 3 over 3, I
believe.
So that, we know, would be equal to 50
root
3 over 3 metres horizontally.
So now we know that y is 50 root 3 over 3
metres.
Now, let's say we wanted to calculate the
distance
traveled vertically.
Let's call this not y, but let's call it
z.
Now, if we know x is 50, because 10 times
is 50, we can actually use the Pythagorean
theorem
to calculate z. That would be no problem.
But
let's try solving for v of y and
confirming
that it does work.
So v of y is this one. So pause the video
and
think, what would be the formula for v of
y?
Well, we know v of y is the opposite of 30
degrees.
So it would be 5 sine 30 degrees.
And we can do that and you would get 2.5.
Sine 30 is 1 over 2. Now, the distance
would
be v of y times t, which would be equal to
2.5
times 10, which would be equal to 25
metres.
So we know that it travels horizontally 25
And this actually makes sense because, let
me
pull up my calculator real quick, because
it
is, ooh, sorry. This should be over 2
because
cosine of 30 is over 2, not over 3.
Sorry, that's my bad. Okay.
Now, let's use the Pythagorean theorem to
confirm
that this works. Well, we actually don't
need
it. We have a 30, 60, 90 triangle over
here.
If you didn't notice, it's 30 metres, 30
degrees
directly to the horizontal. So it's a 1,
2,
root 3 triangle. Is it? Well, here's our
1,
here's our root 3, and here's our 2.
So it does follow it. If you use the
Pythagorean
theorem, you'll find this exact same
thing.
So that basically confirms that we can
split
our velocity and calculate the distance
and
get the right answer. And that's basically
all
for using two-dimensional vectors.
You can use the same thing for
displacement,
for acceleration. Just make sure that
these
are not separate velocities, but they're
just
part of the main velocity itself.
And we use these to calculate horizontally
or
vertically, which can be useful in a lot
of
situations as you will see in the future.
That's
it for today's video, and we'll see you in
the
next one. Bye.